Mohammad Hewedy 📥

Solutions Architect

A confident, self-motivated software architect with more than 11 year of experience in software Engineering and Architecture. A deep researcher and a passionate learner in every aspect of his life, with good analytical and verbal skills.

Contributed () to a number of Open Source projects including Spring AMQP, Spring Data JPA, Castlemock, and others.

Knowledge and experience in may programming Languages and ecosystems including Java, Kotlin, Scala, Groovy, Golang, C, Objective-C, Ruby, JavaScript, TypeScript, C# and others.

Contact Information

mhewedy@gmail.com | Blog | Github | Linkedin

Work Experience

Software Engineer / Lead / Solutions Architect

AL ELM Information Security Company

Nov 2013 – Present Riyadh, Saudi Arabia

Elm Company is a Saudi Joint Stock Company owned by Saudi Public Investment Fund (PIF), it is specialized in providing secure electronic services, and has been in existence since 1988 as a technical research and development lab for the Saudi Ministry of Interior.

Implementing government services while practicing agile methodology to achieve high velocity in delivery in multiple Projects over the past 8+ years.

• Tamm Platform:

Participating in the design, architecture, and implementation of TAMM Platform (TAMM v2.0). Some achievements include

- Participated in the Tamm Revamp docs project.
- Participated in establishing the software practices used by the team (PR, Code Review, etc...) to assure high quality for the produced software.
- Participated in the Design and Architecture of the Tamm Platform.
- Co-Designed and implemented of Async-Await concurrency framework on top of Java/Spring concurrency primitives.
- Co-Designed and implemented spring-data-jpa-mongodb-expressions a library that converts MongoDB queries into SQL queries.

- Created a custom s2i builder image for jdk15 on top of the *Openshift platform*.
- Applying best practices in DDD, TDD, and Clean Architecture

• Architecture and Presales Team:

Working on the Technical presales team to design, document, architect, and price software solutions as a response to RFPs.

• Muqeem (muqeem.sa)/Premium Residency (saprc.gov.sa) :

A portal to allow companies to managing activities for its Residents in saudi arabia with cooperation with Jawazat (General Directorate of Passports).

We are building the next generation of Muqeem using Java, Spring Boot, Netflix SSO (eureka, zuul, hystrix, Ribbon etc...), spring-amqp, RabbitMQ, Redis, Docker, Microservice architecture and wiremock/Castle Mock.

Using: Java 8, Kotlin, Spring Boot (Using JHipster microservice), JWT, Quartz, JPA, RabbitMQ, Redis, SQL Server, Unit & Integration testing, Docker and using atlassian stack.

Marine:

A portal for Public Transport Authority (PTA), it is used to give permission and register activities related to the Marine section in PTA, My role mainly to integrate with Companies Billing System and PTA billing System.

Using: Java 8, Spring Boot (with Spring Data JPA, Security, REST), Hibernate, SQL Server, Apache Tomcat 8 in the backend to expose the app as a secured API, Angular 4 in the frontend and IBM RTC for software-related aspects.

• Mojaz (https://mojaz.com.sa):

A Portal that allows public users to query about car history (including accident history) and print a full report about it, My role mainly to integrate with Companies Billing System and PTA billing System.

Using: Java 8, Spring Boot (Spring Data JPA, Security, REST), Hibernate, SQL Server, Apache Tomcat 8 in the backend to expose the app as a secure API, AngularJS 1.x in the frontend and IBM RTC for software-related aspects.

• ETV (https://etv.com.sa):

A portal for Saudi Commission for Tourism & National Heritage (SCTH), that allows Umrah visa holder to do tourism activities after finishing the Umrah program by changing the sponsor. (many integrations with NIC, Sejel is being included)

Using: Java 8, Spring framework (Security, Data JPA, REST), Hibernate, SQL Server, Apache Tomcat 8 in the backend to expose the app as a secure API, AngularJS in the frontend, Rational Team Concert for SCM and OpenShift (as a PoC); in a team of 3 Developers.

• Basher (https://basher.sa):

Bashir is a compound project, consists of a mobile app that connects to REST service and a Portal to manage users, reports, statistics and other aspects.

Using: Spring framework, (Core, Security, Data JPA), Hibernate, PrimeFaces 5.1 (JSF 2.2), Apache Tomcat 8, JBOSS 7.1 and MS SQL Server.

I worked as the developer responsible for the project working with 1 Senior developer and 2

Junior Developers, working directly with SA, BA, QA and PM.

• TAMM (https://www1.tamm.net.sa/):

TAMM is the project and group of services used by multiple user roles (Car Agencies, Show rooms, etc.) to connect theses users with the Saudi Arabia NIC, I am working on adding new features and maintaining the old features.

Using: JSF 1.2/EJB 3.1, CDI, SOAP and REST services, JWT, JBOSS EAP 6.1 and MS SQL Server.

Software Engineer / Team Leader

SiliconExpert Technologies - an Arrow Electronics Company

Nov 2010 – Nov 2013 Cairo, Egypt

- Headquartered in Santa Clara, is a leading supplier and innovator of best-in-class products and services for enterprise-wide electronic parts management. Customers are: Avago, Exar, Avnet, Arrow, RS, NASA, Dell, Rockwell, and Toshiba.
- I am working directory with our BA to analyze customer requirements and find rapid solutions for customers continuously requests.
- Develop solutions using EJB3.0, JPA, Servlets, JSPs, Custom tags, Filters, XML, JAX-WS, Apache Axis, GWT, JSON, JAX-WS, JavaScript, Apache Lucene, Apache Solr, Android SDK, iOS, Oracle DB, Oracle App Server, tomcat, Spring-jms, git-scm, intellij idea, Eclipse, JIRA, Jenkins and YouTrack

• Build JMS Client to consume logs:

Use Spring JMS to write a log listener to write logs of one of our services into Apache Flume

• Modifying Spark (XMPP client):

Spark is an Open Source, cross-platform Jabber (XMPP) client optimized for businesses and organizations. I was responsible for modifying the app and deliver a windows installation package using install4j/IzPack.

• Arrow Mobile App:

Arrow inc. www.arrow.com is the company that acquired SiliconExpert.

I am acting as a project leader to provide Arrow inc with iOS and Android Mobile Apps.

We are building native mobile apps and building a JSON aggregator Service to call existing modules and provide the functionality for the mobile apps.

• SiliconExpert Mobile App:

Building the Company's iPhone/Android Mobile Application front end and build a JSON Service backed by an EJB module connecting to Oracle DB.

• Avago PartFinder Project:

Integration of some of our services into customer's website through a Widget that is hosted on our domain and deployed into the customer's Web App. The work includes running cross-site JavaScript (Same-origin policy) and many other challenges to make it work on Almost all browsers starting from IE6.0.

• Avago PartFinder Mobile (iPhone/Android):

Converting Avago Application into a Mobile Application(Android and iOS). The work included

converts the Business layer into JSON Services using a custom home-build framework and then consume the JSON services using Mobile Apps.

• Exar Project:

ntegration of some of our services into customer's website.

MainSearch:

A Lucene Manager tool; a tool with a Web-based interface to allow users to search/create/edit/delete indexes.

• Design Center:

Web Application for Electronic Engineers to search for reference designs and other staff they need in designing Electronic Circuits.

The work includes investigating on the issue of Search engine optimization (SEO) and crawling for Ajax Applications.

• Worked on securing companies web services (using HTTPS) and writing clients to consume these web services

Software Engineer

CyberSource a VISA Company

April 2009 – Nov 2010 Cairo, Egypt

- Headquartered in Mountain View, California, is a leading provider of electronic payment and risk management services
- Responsible for Design and implement ePayment Solutions
- Worked with payment services like, Auth, Bill, Credit, Refund, many of PayPal Services and others
- Develop solutions using Java, C, Servlets, XML, XSLT, XPath, JPos, JBoss, Linux, Rational ClearCase and AccuRev
- Fixed Major encoding issue in China PayEase gateway simulator
- Worked on many PayPal bug fixes. (PayPal EC and Button create service)
- Worked on bug fixes for other Payment gateways as well including Paymentech and APACS30 gateways

Software Engineer

ElRowad

Jan 2009 – April 2009 Cairo, Egypt

• Responsible for the Design and Implementation of company's own Stock Management software

Education

B.S. Computers and Information

Helwan University, Cairo Egypt Sept 2007

Grade: Very Good

Certifications

 AWS Certified Solutions Architect – Associate Amazon Web Services Aug 2020

License: SAA

• Certified Kubernetes Application Developer The Linux Foundation

Jun 2020

License: CKAD-2000-004804-0100

• TOGAF® 9 Certified The Open Group

Jan 2020

License: 140538

• TOGAF® 9 Foundation

The Open Group

Nov 2019

License: 603233

 DevOps Leader DevOps Institute April 2019

License: GR685000296MH

 DevOps Foundation DevOps Institute

April 2019

License: GR797009838MH

Skills

- Good understanding of OOP & Functional style programming
- Behavior / Test Driven Development Unit, Integration, System Testing
- Agile Methodologies Scrum, Kanban
- Good understanding of type theory and the programming paradigm
- Good knowledge about JVM echo system (Kotlin, Groovy, and Scala)

- Good knowledge about other languages as well (C, Objective-C, Ruby, RoR, Golang, and Nodejs)
- Background knowledge in other languages as well (C#, VB.net, C++, PL-SQL)
- Good knowledge in Linux Configuration & shell scripting
- Java (Threading, Networking, JDBC, RMI, JPA)
- Basic understanding of the some compilers architecture, e.g. GCC, LLVM, GraalVM and others
- Web (JSP&Servlets, Struts, JSF, Freemarker, MVC, Front-Controller, etc).
- Distributed Programming (App Servers, EJB and JNDI) and messaging (RabbitMQ, JMS, Apache Camel).
- A good background in Web Services (SOAP-based and RESTful) and XML (SAX, DOM, XSLT, XPath)
- Good knowledge about the internals of Spring framework, Hibernate, Spring Security, Spring Data (JPA, Mongo), Spring Boot and Spring AMQP.
- Experience Mobile Programming (Android /iPhone)
- Experience with full-Stack Web Development (Angular, Vue.js, Mustache.js, and others)
- Good understand parallelism and concurrency and related patterns (e.g. CSP) and its implementations in golang and kotlin
- Basic knowledge Linux programming (syscalls, strace, LKM, LSM, filesystems, namespaces and others)
- Basic understanding of the different storage types (object, block, file) and its use cases
- Basic understanding Hypervisors and containerization (the theory and practices)
- Good understanding of RDBMS, NoSQL databases, Big Data and Database Sharding techniques
- Basic knowledge about NoSQL solutions such as Cassandra and Couchbase
- Basic understanding of Data Engineering processes
- Experience with Searching solutions (Apache Lucene/Solr)
- Familiarity with Big Data and Stream processing solutions such as Apache Hadoop, Hive, Pig, and Apache Spark
- Experience in RDBMS and ORM Oracle, SQL Server, MySQL, PostgreSQL
- Experience in NoSQL MongoDB
- Basic understanding of ISO 8601, Unicode and other related standards.
- Basic understanding of OSI model and related protocols (TCP, UDP, DNS, ARP, FTP, SSH, TLS), and basic knowledge about networking tools like iptables, iproute2, wireshark, tcpdump, and more.
- Good understanding of digital cryptography.
- Good understanding of ESB, EAI, Queues, BPM, and related enterprise solutions and patterns
- Hands-on experience in Jenkins, Bitbucket pipelines, Docker, Docker Compose, Kubernetes, GCP and AWS.
- Basic knowledge about Machine Learning

Trainings

- · Openshift Workshop
- Identity and Access management
- Functional Programming Principles in Scala (Coursera online)
- Develop iOS apps using Swift
- AngularJS 2
- Securing Java Applications
- · Agile Software methodology
- Developing for the Liferay Platform 1

Open Source Projects 🗘

- Spring Data JPA MongoDB Expressions Allows you to use the MongoDB query syntax to query your relational database.
- ci-pipeline 🖓 Opinionated Jenkins Pipeline in YAML
- vermin The smart virtual machines manager.
- SBO-video-extension Safari Books Online Video Downloder Extension to Google Chrome.
- spwrap 🜎 Simple Stored Procedure call wrapper with no framework dependencies.
- ews 🔾 Go package wrapper for Exchange Web Service (EWS)
- gitblame Simple Web Application to show each member in team work in a web-based interface
- agarme Service to query https://sa.agar.fm/ for certain criteria and notifies me back by Facebook messenger on the list of apartments that matches my criteria.
- mego 🖸 The MS Exchange meeting organizer

Volunteering Experience

Riyadh Java Meetup (Founder)

April 2019 – Present Riyadh, Saudi Arabia

• The Riyadh Java Meetup is a meetup concerted about Java and the JVM, with the main focus is on Spring framework and spring boot.

k8s Araby Meetup (Co-founder)

July 2020 – Present Riyadh, Saudi Arabia

Languages

- Arabic Native
- English Professional working proficiency